Guide to the Sauer, Farrell, & Co. Records, 1870-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Sauer, Farrell & Co. records 1870-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Sauer, Farrell, & Co.
3.5 Linear Feet 45 Items
Sauer, Farrell, & Co. was a cigar manufacturing company located in Suffield, Connecticut, during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Collection of ledgers, account books, order forms, and other ephemera relating to the sale and purchase of cigars by Sauer, Farrell, & Co., Cigar Manufacturers. Materials range in date from the 1870s through the early 1900s, and it is believed that the cigar company may have changed names throughout that period. The centerpiece of the collection is a specimen book of sample cigar box labels, created by the lithographers Heppenheimer & Maurer around 1878. The specimen book includes about 115 leaves, with labels affixed on each side of the leaf; the label colors range from two colors to multiple colors per label. Account books document cigar production, purchase, and sales information. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sauer, Farrell, & Co. Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2008.
Historical Note
Sauer, Farrell, & Co. was a cigar manufacturing company located in Suffield, Connecticut, during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Suffield was the site of the country's first cigar factory, which opened in 1810 after its owners hired a Cuban to teach its workers how to roll tobacco. The town became home to numerous factories that used local crops and sold a variety of cigars throughout the eastern United States. Not much is known about Sauer, Farrell, & Co. in particular, but its involvement in cigar manufacturing and selling appear to reflect the general activities of Suffield cigar factories during this time.
Heppenheimer & Maurer was a lithography company that created box labels for cigar manufacturers to paste on the inside lid of a box of cigars. Sample books like the one in this collection were distributed to local cigar manufacturers, who could then order the labels by their designated number. Frederick Heppenheimer, from New York City, was one of the earliest and most prolific commerical lithographers. He later partnered with Louis Maurer, another well-regarded artist, to create Heppenheimer & Maurer in 1872. Maurer was one of the few cigar label lithographers who regularly signed his work. The company was one of dozens of lithography companies from this period whose art reflected everyday life in the United States.
Collection Overview
Collection of ledgers, account books, order forms, and other ephemera relating to the sale and purchase of cigars by Sauer, Farrell, & Co., Cigar Manufacturers. Materials range in date from the 1870s through the early 1900s, and it is believed that the cigar company may have changed names throughout that period. The centerpiece of the collection is a specimen book of sample cigar box labels, created by the lithographers Heppenheimer & Maurer around 1878. The specimen book includes about 115 leaves, with labels affixed on each side of the leaf; the color ranges from two colors to multiple colors per label. Account books document cigar production, purchase, and sales information. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Maurer, Louis, 1832-1932
Heppenheimer, Frederick, d. 1876
Heppenheimer & Maurer
Suffield (Conn.) -- Commerce
Advertising -- Tobacco
Advertising -- Tobacco -- History
Advertising -- Tobacco -- United States -- History
Cigar box labels -- United States -- History
Cigar box labels -- United States -- Specimens
Cigars -- History -- United States
Cigars -- Miscellanea
Commercial art
Lithographers
Lithography, American
Sample books -- United States -- 19th century
Tobacco -- Connecticut -- Marketing
Tobacco package labels -- United States
Account books
Ledgers
Labels (identifying artifacts)
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Cigar Label Specimen Book, 1878, 1 Box
  Specimen book created by Heppenheimer & Maurer, dated approximately 1878, and distributed to Sauer, Farrell, & Co. Book contains about 120 pages with labels pasted on each side of each page. Each label has a four-digit number stamped in blue ink, ranging from the 1600s to the 7000s. The labels are not in numerical order. The book and its pages are in fair condition; the book's binding needs preservation work, the back cover is detached, and some pages are dirty. The labels' lithographs are in excellent condition, many with vibrant colors. The artwork is generally very bright with subjects tending towards an exotic or tropical feel.
  - Cigar Label Specimen Book (Box 1)
- Sauer, Farrell & Co. Materials, 1870s-2008 and undated, 9 Boxes
  Includes order forms, account ledgers, sample cigar wrappers, receipts, and one photograph from the Sauer, Farrell & Co. cigar manufacturing company. The account ledgers represent the bulk of the series, recording cigar production, purchase, and sales information. Also includes auction house catalogs describing the collection.
  - Account ledgers
    - 1874-1885 (Box 2)
    - 1885-1893 (Box 3)
    - 1880-1881 (Box 4)
    - 1891-1899 (Front cover is missing.) (Box 5)
  - Cigar manufacturer's books, 1891-1937 (Used by P.J. Farrell) (Box 6)
    - 1891-1893
    - 1926-1928
      [Includes loose inventories and correspondence.]
  - Account ledger, 1886-1893 (Box 7)
  - Auction materials related to collection, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Farrell notices against fraud
  - Photograph of Sauer, Farrell, & Co. factory, 1888
    [Features company's building with employees posed outside. Bottom left corner is missing.]
  - Tobacco invoice forms, blank, undated
  - Account ledgers (Box 9)
    - 1870-1871
    - 1886 (Includes receipts and statements from P.S. Lipps of Suffield, Conn., stuck inside the ledger's cover.)
    - 1888-1890
    - 1890-1902 (Tracking sales per month. Missing a cover.)
  - Seasonal advertisements, C.B. Henschel Manufacturing Co., 1932-1937, (2 folders) (Box 10)